Finding Aid for University of Michigan admissions lawsuits collection, 1995-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Gratz v. Bollinger, et al., 1997-2007
  - Defendants' Motion and Memorandum of Law in Support of Defendants' Motion for Order Denying Class Certification September 8, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and for Bifurcation of Liability and Damages Trials October 9, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Memorandum of Law in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and for Bifurcation October 9, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Order Granting Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and Bifurcation December 23, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Opinion Granting Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and Bifurcation December 23, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Sixth Circuit Court Ruling Allowing Intervention August 10, 1999 (Box 17)
  - Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment on Liability July 17, 2000 (Box 17)
  - "General Motors Corporation Files Amicus Brief in Support of the University of Michigan's Defense of Its Admissions Policies," July 17, 2000 (Box 17)
  - Fortune 500 Corporations Motion for Leave to File Brief as Amici Curiae in Support of Defendants and Briefs October 16, 2000 (Box 17)
  - Opinion of Judge Patrick J. Duggan Regarding Motions for Summary Judgment December 13, 2000 (Box 17)
  - Order and Opinion of Judge Patrick J. Duggan Granting Plaintiffs' Motion for Summary Judgment with Respect to Defendant-Intervenors' Claims February 26, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Plaintiffs-Appellants'/Plaintiffs-Appellees' Brief on Appeal May 7, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Business, Education and Social Justice Organizations File Amicus Brief in Support of the University of Michigan's Defense of Its Admissions Policies June 13, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Final Brief of Defendants-Appellees July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Final Reply Brief of Appellees and Appellants July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Pleadings
    - Plaintiffs' Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability April 8, 1999 (Box 17)
    - Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity, April July 15 2000 (Box 17)
    - Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment as to Plaintiffs' Claims for Injunctive and Declaratory Relief, July, 15 2000 (Box 17)
    - Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability and Memorandum in Support July 17, 2000
      - Supplemental Memorandum in Support of Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability July 17, 2000 (Box 17)
    - Defendant-Intervenors' Response to Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment as to Plaintiffs' Claims for Declaratory and Injunctive Relief August 10, 2000 (Box 17)
    - Defendant-Intervenors' Response in Opposition to Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment August 10, 2000 (Box 17)
    - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' Two Renewed Motions for Summary Judgment and Reply Memorandum in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability August 10, 2000
      - Affidavit of Kirk O. Kolbo and Exhibits Submitted in Support of Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' Two Renewed Motions for Summary Judgment and Reply Memorandum in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability August 4, 2000 (Box 17)
  - Final Briefs 2001
    - Final Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellees July 25, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Reply Brief of Appellees and Appellants July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Brief of Defendants-Appellees July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Brief of Defendants-Intervenors/Appellants July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Reply Brief for Defendant-Intervenors Appellees July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Brief of Defendant-Intervenors/Appellees July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellants and Plaintiffs-Appellees July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Reply Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellants and Final Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellees July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Final Brief of Appellees and Appellants July 30, 2001 (Box 17)
  - First Amended Motion to Intervene February 10, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Reply Memorandum of Proposed Intervenors March 4, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Motion to Hear Oral Argument on Motion to Intervene June 5, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Motion for Reconsideration July 21, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Reply Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Motion for Reassignment or, Alternatively, for Designating Actions as Companion Cases July 29, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Opinion Designating Gratz and Grutter as Companion Cases, August 6, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Supplemental Memorandum in Support of Motion for Reconsideration August 14, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion to Certify a Class Action & to Bifurcate Liability from Damages September 10, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Motions of Proposed Defendant-Intervenors to Supplement the Record and to Stay District Court Proceedings May 19, 1999 (Box 22)
  - Exhibits in Support of Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion to Strike Any Testimony or Expert Opinions (including William Bowen) Based on Consideration of the College and Beyond Database (Box 22)
  - Appendix in Support of Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment Regarding Plaintiffs' Claims for Injunctive & Declaratory Relief & Renewed Motion for Defendants Bollinger & Duderstadt for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity July 15, 2000, 5 volumes (Box 22)
  - Appendix in Support of Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment and Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Cross-Motion for Summary Judgment, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Answer to Defendants' Petition to Appeal or for a Writ of Mandamus and Motion to Expedite Appeal May 9, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Petition for Permission to Appeal or for a Writ of Mandamus and Motion to Consolidate May 10, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Affidavit of Kirk O. Kolbo and Exhibits in Support of Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability June 9, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Brief of National Association of Scholars as Amicus Curiae in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment July 14, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Motion of National Association of Scholars for Leave to File Brief as Amicus Curiae in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment July 14, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Motion to Strike Any Testimony or Expert Opinions (including William Bowen) Based on Consideration of the College and Beyond Database July 17, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' two renewed motions for summary judgment & reply memo in support of Plaintiffs' motion for partial summary judgment on liability August 4, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Defendant-Intervenors' Response to Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment, August 10 2000 (Box 23)
  - Defendant-Intervenors' Response to Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment as to Plaintiff's Claims for Declaratory & Injunctive Relief August 10, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Answer to Petition and Cross-Petition February 16, 2001 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Response to Intervenors' Motion for Entry of a Rule 54(b) or 28 U.S.C. 129(b) order (Box 23)
  - Proof Reply Brief of Appellees and Appellants July 2, 2001 (Box 23)
  - Final Brief of Appellees & Appellants July 30, 2001 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Renewed Motion and Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity July 15, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Interrogatories to Defendant (Set I) December 24, 1997 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Request for Production of Documents to Defendants (Set I) December 24, 1997 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories to Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories to Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions to Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production to Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions to Patrick Hamacher February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production to Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Objections and Responses to Interrogatories #3-9 of Plaintiffs' Interrogatories to Defendants' (Set I) March 10, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Objections and Responses to Plaintiffs' Requests for Production of Documents to Defendants (Set I) March 20, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher's Response and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions April 1, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz's Responses and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions April 1, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher's Objections and Answers to Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories April 3, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz's Objections and Answers to Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories April 3, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Objections and Responses to Interrogatories #1, 2 and 10-14 of Plaintiffs' Interrogatories to Defendants (Set I) April 7, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz's Responses and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production of Documents April 29, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Unopposed Stipulation for Protective Order Concerning Confidentiality May 27, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher's Responses and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production of Documents April 29, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Amended Objections and Responses to Plaintiffs' Requests for Production of Documents to Defendants (Set I) June 26, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Transcript of Oral Argument, Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals December 6, 2001, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Petition for Writ of Certiorari Before Judgment to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit October 1, 2002 (Box 23)
  - Intervenors' Petition for Writ of Certiorari in Gratz, October 14, 2002 (Box 23)
  - UM Response to Plaintiffs' Petition for Writ of Certiorari Before Judgment to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit October 29, 2002 (Box 23)
  - UM Response to Intervenors' Petition for Writ of Certiorari in Gratz, October 29, 2002 (Box 23)
  - Brief for Petitioners, U.S. Supreme Court January 16, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Brief for Respondents, U.S. Supreme Court February 18, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Brief for Intervenors Patterson, et al., U.S. Supreme Court February 18, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Petitioner's Reply Brief March 25, 2003 (Box 24)
  - U.S. Supreme Court Docket Gratz v. Bollinger, et al (Box 24)
  - U.S. Supreme Court Decision in Gratz v. Bollinger, June 23, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Reply Brief in Support of their Motion for an Interim Award of Attorney's Fees and Costs Pursuant to 42 U.S.C. sec 1988 October 1, 2004 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Reply Brief in Support of Motion to Allow Limited Discovery Related to Fees and Costs November 19, 2004 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiff' Motion and Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion for Class Certification and Partial Summary Judgment with Respect to Certain Nominal and Incidental Damages Claims; and for Certification of a Subclass to Determine Compensatory Damages Claims December 8, 2004 (Box 24)
  - Defendants' Response to Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability and to Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and Partial Summary Judgment with Respect to Certain Nominal and Incidental Damages Claims January 19, 2005 (Box 24)
  - U.S. District Judge Patrick J. Duggan's Opinion in Plaintiffs' Motion for an Award of Attorney's Fees and Costs January 27, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Combined 1) Reply Memorandum in Support of Motion for Partial Summary Judgment and Motion for Class Certification and Partial Summary Judgment with Respect to Certain Nominal Incidental Damages Claims; and 2) Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' Motion for a Stay January 28, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Brief Regarding 1) Burden of Proof; 2) Legal Standard; and 3) Standing February 2, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Defendants' Response to Plaintiffs' Brief Regarding 1) Standing; 2) Burden of Proof; and 3) Legal Standard March 23, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Reply Brief Regarding 1) Burden of Proof; 2) Legal Standard; and 3) Standing April 6, 2005 (Box 24)
  - U.S. District Court Judge Patrick J. Duggan's Opinion in Plaintiffs' Motion Regarding 1) Burden of Proof; 2) Legal Standard; and 3) Standing August 5, 2005 (Box 24)
  - U.S. District Court Judge Patrick J. Duggan's Order Approving Settlement and Notice Plan, Decertifying Class, and Dismissing Case January 31, 2007 (Box 24)
  - District Court Amici Curiae Briefs
    - Attorney General Jennifer Granholm (Box 24)
    - College Board (Box 24)
    - State of Ohio (Box 24)
    - United States (Box 24)
  - Supreme Court Briefs
    - Brief for Respondents (Box 24)
    - Briefs in Support of Respondents Gratz
      - American Council on Education (Box 24)
      - American Educational Research Association, et al. (Box 24)
      - American Federation of Labor, et al. (Box 24)
      - American Jewish Committee, et al. (Box 24)
      - American Psychological Association (Box 24)
      - Amherst University, et al. (Box 24)
      - Authors of the Texas 10% Plan (Box 24)
      - Bay Mills Indian Community, et al. (Box 24)
      - Lt. General Julius W. Becton, Jr. (Retired Military) (Box 24)
      - Black Women Lawyers Association (Box 24)
      - Carnegie Mellon University, et al. (Box 24)
      - City of Philadelphia, et al (Box 24)
      - College Board (Box 24)
      - Columbia University, et al. (Box 24)
      - Representative John Conyers and other Members of Congress (Box 24)
      - General Motors (Box 24)
      - Harvard University, et al. (Box 24)
      - New American Alliance (Box 24)
      - New York City Council Speaker G. Miller, et al. (Box 24)
      - Northeastern University (Box 24)
      - NOW Legal Defense & Education Fund, et al. (Box 24)
      - Representative Richard Gephardt, et al. (Box 24)
      - Senators Thomas A. Daschle, et al. (Box 24)
      - Social Scientists Glenn C. Loury, et al. (Box 24)
      - State of New Jersey (Box 24)
      - States of Maryland, et al. (Box 24)
      - 3M, et al. (Box 24)
      - United Negro College Fund, et al. (Box 24)
      - University of Pittsburgh, et al. (Box 24)
      - Hayden Family (Box 24)
      - Howard University (Box 25)
      - Human Rights Advocates, et al. (Box 25)
      - Latino Organizations (Box 25)
      - Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights, et al. (Box 25)
      - Leadership Conference on Civil Rights (Box 25)
      - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, et al. (Box 25)
      - Media Companies (Box 25)
      - Members of the United States Congress (Box 25)
      - Michigan Governor Jennifer Granholm (Box 25)
      - MTV Networks (Box 25)
      - National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium, et al. (Box 25)
      - National Coalition of Blacks for Reparations (Box 25)
      - National Education Association, et al. (Box 25)
      - National School Boards Association, et al. (Box 25)
      - National Urban League, et al. (Box 25)
    - Briefs in Support of Petitioners Gratz
      - Asian American Legal Foundation (Box 25)
      - Cato Institute (Box 25)
      - Center for Equal Opportunity, The Independent Women's Forum, and American Civil Rights Institute (Box 25)
      - Center for Individual Freedom (Box 25)
      - Center for New Black Leadership (Box 25)
      - Center for the Advancement of Capitalism (Box 25)
      - Claremont Institute (Box 25)
      - Duane C. Ellison (Box 25)
      - Law Professors (Box 25)
      - Michigan Association of Scholars (Box 25)
      - National Association of Scholars (Box 25)
      - Pacific Legal Foundation (Box 25)
      - Reason Foundation (Box 25)
      - State of Florida (Box 25)
      - United States (Box 25)
      - Ward Connerly (Box 25)
    - Briefs in Support of Neither Party
      - Anti-Defamation League (Box 25)
      - BP America Inc. (Box 25)
      - Equal Employment Advisory Council (Box 25)
  - Expert Reports
    - Lerner, Barbara (Box 25)
    - Raudenbush, Stephen (Box 25)
    - Rudolph, Jim (Box 25)
    - Silver, Jacob (Box 25)
    - Sugrue, Thomas (Box 25)
    - Trent, William (Box 25)
    - Welsh, Finis (Box 25)
  - Compelling Need for Diversity in Higher Education (Box 25)
  - On Appeal from the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan (Duggan, J.), Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals, Joint Appendix, 9 volumes (Box 26)
- News Media 1995-2003
  The News Media series, 1995-2003 (2 linear feet) consists of articles, editorials and electronic mail communications. The series provides a glimpse of the media attention the two lawsuits attracted across the country. The articles and editorials are clippings on the affirmative action lawsuits from newspapers and journals from across the United States. The articles and editorials include newspaper clippings (photocopy), print-outs from webpages, and press releases (photocopy). Included in the series is a copy of Newsweek magazine January 27, 2003 which featured the affirmative action lawsuits as the cover story. The electronic mail communications are print-outs of communications sent either from University of Michigan President Mary Sue Coleman or from the Office of Media Relations and Public Affairs. The electronic mail communications were targeted messages to the university community. The communications date from December 2002 to June 2003.
  The News Media series also includes a selection of actual copies of newspapers and articles for significant events. Dates are scattered but include copies of area newspapers for June 24, 2003--the day after the Supreme Court decision. The series includes a paper copy of the official Press Kit dated March 2003 created by the university's Media Relations and Public Affairs office (note that a digital copy of the Press Kit for selected dates can be found in the Archived Website series). Lastly, the series includes a paper copy of the complete transcript from the oral arguments before the U.S. Supreme Court on April 1, 2003 in Grutter v. Bollinger, et al and Gratz and Hamacher v. Bollinger, et. al. as recorded by Alderson Reporting Co. and published by the Ann Arbor News.
  The series is largely the reference file maintained by Julie Peterson, Associate Vice President for Media Relations, University of Michigan, with some additional clippings collected by the University Archives and Records Program staff from a variety of sources.
  - 1995 (Box 18)
    - Articles, 1 folder (Box 18)
  - 1996
    - Articles, 1 folder (Box 18)
  - 1997
    - Articles, 1 folder (Box 18)
  - 1998
    - Articles, 1 folder (Box 18)
  - 1999
    - Articles, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 2000
    - Articles, 4 folders (Box 18)
    - Editorials, 1 folder (Box 18)
  - 2001
    - Articles, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Editorials, 1 folder (Box 18)
  - 2002
    - Articles, 1 folder (Box 19)
    - Editorials, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - 2003
    - Articles, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Editorials, 1 folder (Box 19)
  - Electronic Mail Communications, paper print-outs, (2002-2003) (Box 19)
  - Newspapers, original versions, scattered dates, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Newsweek, January 27, 2003 (Box 19)
  - Transcript of Oral Arguments before the U.S. Supreme Court in Grutter v. Bollinger, et al and Gratz and Hamacher v. Bollinger, et al. published by Ann Arbor News, April 1, 2003 (Box 19)
- Archived Admissions Lawsuit Website
  - February 25, 2002 capture
    The Admissions Lawsuits website series, 1997-2003 (2 CD-ROMs) consists of a number of strategically planned snapshots of the University of Michigan's Admissions Lawsuits website. Each of the snapshots are described as a subseries and are distinguished by the date the snapshot of the website was taken. A snapshot is defined as a point-in-time capture of the material available on the website. There are four subseries, one for each snapshot. February 25, 2002 (approx. 400 digital records, 23.1 MB), February 25, 2003 (approx. 1,200 digital records, 97.4 MB), March 31, 2003 (approx. 70 digital records, 11.1 MB) and September 16, 2003 (approx. 800 digital records, 174 MB).
    The Admissions Lawsuits website was designed by the Office of Marketing Communications for the Office of Media Relations and Public Affairs. Both offices are part of the Vice President for Communications. The purpose of the website was to serve as a convenient access point for the dissemination of documents relating to the two lawsuits to a broad audience. The series offers a wealth of information both on the background of the cases, including references to supporting research, as well as, full-text copies of the court documents for both lawsuits dating from 1997 to 2003.
    The Admissions Lawsuit Website snapshots were captured by the University Archives using the software application Teleport Pro. The original structure and presentation of the website have been maintained. Thus, the organization and arrangement of the website is based on the original directory structure of the website (e.g. What's New, Legal Overview, Court Filings, and Statement from University Leaders).
    Content of links external to the University of Michigan Admissions Lawsuits website (http://www.umich.edu/~urel/admissions) have for the most part not been included in the website series. Content external to the main Universal Resource Locator (URL) address may have originally been to other websites or webpages within the umich.edu domain, to a personal faculty website, or to another institution, organization or research project. A citation to the original URL for the documents and/or webpages that were not captured can be found within the original source code. In addition, there were a few files that were not available at the time of the website capture. This may be due to a changed URL address since the time the document was originally linked to the website or due to technical difficulty in capturing a specific page, image, or document.
    - University of Michigan. Admissions Lawsuits Website. (Box 2)
      (Original source http://www.umich.edu/~urel/admissions)
      - What's New May 2001-December 2001 (Box 2)
      - Legal Documents
        - Gratz and Hamacher v. Bollinger, et al. October 1997-July 2001 (Box 2)
        - Grutter v. Bollinger, et al. December 1997-July 2001 (Box 2)
      - Articles in the University Record, 1997-2001 (reference index) (Box 2)
      - Comments by University Leaders 1997-2002 (Box 2)
      - Statements of Support 1997-2000 (Box 2)
  - February 25, 2003 capture
    - University of Michigan. Admissions Lawsuits Website (Box 3)
      - What's New May 2002-February 2003 (Box 3)
      - Legal Overview May 2002-March 2003 (Box 3)
      - Court Filings December 1997-February 2003 (Box 3)
      - Supporting Research January 1999-July 2001 (Box 3)
      - FAQs November 2000-February 2003 (Box 3)
      - Press Kit February 2003 (Box 3)
      - Statements by University Leaders and Others May 2001-February 2003 (Box 3)
      - News and Information Services Press Releases and University Record, October 1997-February 2003 (reference index) (Box 3)
      - En Espanol! December 2002-February 2003 (Box 3)
    - President Bush Discusses Michigan Affirmative Action Case January 16, 2003 (Box 3)
      (Original source: http://www.whitehouse.gov)
    - Office of Undergraduate Admissions, University of Michigan, as of January 29, 2003 (Box 3)
      (Original source: http://www.admissions.umich.edu)
    - Law School Admissions Office, as of February 6, 2003 (Box 3)
      (Original source: http://www.law.umich.edu/prospectivestudents/Admissions/index.htm)
  - March 31, 2003 capture